<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="https://www.rssboard.org/media-rss">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on 陶语冰的博客</title>
    <link>https://shorterthandijkstra.github.io/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thoughts on 陶语冰的博客</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://shorterthandijkstra.github.io/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><icon>https://shorterthandijkstra.github.io/img/icon.svg</icon>
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://shorterthandijkstra.github.io/thoughts/not_getting_enough_deep_sleep_may_increase_the_risk_of_developing_dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shorterthandijkstra.github.io/thoughts/not_getting_enough_deep_sleep_may_increase_the_risk_of_developing_dementia/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<h3 id="title">title</h3>
<p>Not getting enough deep sleep may increase the risk of developing dementia</p>
<h3 id="url">url</h3>
<h1 id="heading"></h1>
<p><a href="https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/not-getting-enough-deep-sleep-may-increase-dementia-risk#Clarifying-the-link-between-sleep,-aging,-and-dementia-risk">https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/not-getting-enough-deep-sleep-may-increase-dementia-risk#Clarifying-the-link-between-sleep,-aging,-and-dementia-risk</a></p>
<h3 id="vocabulary">vocabulary</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>dementia</p>
<p>an illness that affects the brain and memory, and makes you gradually lose the ability to think and behave normally</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>prevalence</p>
<p>existing very commonly or happening often</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>curative</p>
<p>able to or intended to cure illness</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>screen</p>
<p>a medical test to see whether someone has an illness</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>metabolism</p>
<p>all the chemical processes in your body, especially those that cause food to be used for energy and growth</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>replenish</p>
<p>to put new supplies into something, or to fill something again</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>sedation</p>
<p>the use of drugs to make someone calm or go to sleep</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="summary">summary</h3>
<h5 id="what-is-deep-sleep">what is deep sleep</h5>
<p>Sleep consists of four main cycles: three cycles of non-REM (rapid eye movement) sleep and one cycle of REM sleep.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Stage 1 (Non-REM)</strong>: Light sleep, where you drift in and out of consciousness. Muscle activity slows down, and you may experience sudden muscle contractions (hypnic jerks). Brain waves begin to slow down from their wakeful state.</li>
<li><strong>Stage 2 (Non-REM)</strong>: The onset of true sleep. Brain waves continue to slow down with occasional bursts of rapid waves known as sleep spindles. Body temperature decreases, and heart rate slows down.</li>
<li><strong>Stage 3 (Non-REM)</strong>: Deep sleep, also known as slow-wave sleep. This stage is characterized by very slow brain waves (delta waves). It&rsquo;s difficult to wake someone from deep sleep, and this stage is crucial for physical restoration, immune function, and memory consolidation.</li>
<li><strong>REM Sleep</strong>: Rapid Eye Movement sleep, where dreaming occurs. Brain activity increases to near waking levels, but the body remains paralyzed (except for eye movements and minor muscle twitches). Heart rate and breathing become irregular, and this stage is important for emotional processing and memory consolidation.</li>
</ol>
<h5 id="why-does-deep-sleep-affect-dementia">why does deep sleep affect dementia</h5>
<p>Deep sleep is closely linked to brain health, and its role in affecting dementia is multifaceted:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Memory Consolidation</strong>: Deep sleep is crucial for memory consolidation, where the brain processes and stores information gathered during wakefulness. This process helps in retaining memories and learning new information. Inadequate deep sleep can impair this function, leading to memory difficulties and cognitive decline, which are early signs of dementia.</li>
<li><strong>Brain Waste Clearance</strong>: During deep sleep, the glymphatic system becomes more active. This system clears waste products from the brain, including toxic proteins such as beta-amyloid. Beta-amyloid is known to accumulate in the brains of individuals with Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease, a common form of dementia. Proper deep sleep facilitates the efficient removal of these toxins, potentially reducing the risk of developing dementia.</li>
<li><strong>Brain Structure and Function</strong>: Deep sleep is essential for maintaining the integrity and health of brain cells and neural networks. It supports neuronal repair, growth, and synaptic plasticity, all of which are critical for optimal brain function. Disruptions in deep sleep can compromise these processes, contributing to neurodegenerative changes associated with dementia.</li>
<li><strong>Impact on Cognitive Function</strong>: Adequate deep sleep supports various cognitive functions, including attention, problem-solving, and decision-making. Chronic sleep deprivation or poor quality sleep can impair these functions, exacerbating cognitive decline and increasing the risk of dementia over time.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="tips-for-better-sleep">tips for better sleep</h3>
<p>Things that can improve the quality of sleep: reducing stress before bedtime, taking a warm shower or bath, sleeping in a cooler room, avoiding screen time in the afternoon and evening, and using blue light filter.</p>
<p>Traditional sedatives like sleeping pills do not improve sleep quality or duration, including deep sleep. They may trick the brain into believing sleep was better than it was, but research shows they only marginally increase total sleep time by a few minutes per night.</p>
]]></description>
      
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://shorterthandijkstra.github.io/thoughts/%E6%89%8B%E6%9C%BA%E5%A4%A7%E8%84%91/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shorterthandijkstra.github.io/thoughts/%E6%89%8B%E6%9C%BA%E5%A4%A7%E8%84%91/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="进化的惯性">进化的惯性</h1>
<p>很多人有过这样的经历：在明明已经吃饱的情况下，面对美味的食物，还想继续吃下去，即使理性告诉自己，再吃下去对身体不好。人为什么会有这样的欲望？人类所有的欲望都和进化有关。在生产力不发达的时代，很多人要面临饥饿的威胁。看到树上的果子，有的人吃饱后就离开了，第二天饿了再来，树上已经没有了果子。而有的人吃饱后还想继续吃，他们无疑有更大的生存几率。人类从诞生到现在，有多少时间需要面对饥饿的挑战？我没有考证过，考虑到今天仍然有人营养不良，我猜测这段时间的比例很大。虽然现在很多国家都没有饥饿的问题了，但是因为人类的温饱时代太短，大脑还不能适应新的环境。人吃饱了还想吃，是因为在漫长的历史中，这样的人能更好地存活下来。即使现在人类已经进入不愁吃喝的时代，但是这段时间太短，我们还保留了这样的欲望。</p>
<p>进化是一条遥迢千里的河流，个人只是河流上的一滴水，个人无法克服食欲，也无法克服性欲，这是古希腊掌管进化的神给的设定。</p>
]]></description>
      
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
